Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna's course.
Let's begin.
This is Chapter 17,
LAS KYI BRTAGS PA.
This is an investigation into the nature of karma
and the seeds of karma.
We took a look and
found this chapter rather unusual
because we finally understand what it's about,
and it doesn't even seem like Nagarjuna's style. Do
n't worry, he'll confuse us again later.
I personally
kept wondering why he would discuss the
Abhidharma's introduction to karma
and divide karma into motivation,
and motivated actions and words.
Then he talked about some obscure Abhidharma concepts
about different types of karma.
For example, you can see a person's motivation,
or an aura, or a kind of halo that forms around them,
whether good or bad.
That's another kind of karma. Does
someone want to earn $100?
Guess why he's talking about
these obscure and difficult-to-understand concepts of karma in the Abhidharma.
[A faint voice of reply]
No, why?
Why did he do that?
[A faint voice of reply]
The answer is simpler than that.
[Student] Because everyone is a student of Abhidharma.
Excellent!  How much did I just say?  One hundred US dollars?
[Student] Yes,
Patch got $100. Don't forget to tell Elizabeth. Yes, back
then, for about seven hundred years,
everyone was a student of Abhidharma.
Then he tried to overturn that wave.
By the way, he actually did it, all by
himself.
He faced a
vast ocean of Abhidharma "accountants"
and turned them all into hippies. Yeah,
okay.
He continues.
We'd like to know if you remember
why he didn't talk about the ten wholesome deeds
and the ten non-wholesome deeds.
Guess what he'll do next?
Ready?
,DKAR PO'I LAS KYI LAM BCU PO,
,CHOS SGRUB PA YI THABS YIN TE,
,CHOS KYI 'BRAS BU 'DI GZHAN DU,
,'DOD PA'I YON TAN RNAM LNGA'O,
DKAR PO'I LAS refers to virtuous deeds or good deeds.
LAM BCU PO -- 10 paths, that
is, ten kinds of virtuous deeds. The
ten precepts in Buddhism
are called the Ten Virtuous Deeds.
CHOS SGRUB ... CHOS SGRUB PA YI THABS
These are the methods to achieve the Dharma.
Then Master Chögyal says that the
Dharma mentioned by the enlightened Nagarjuna here
refers to higher rebirth and ultimate
goodness. Ultimate goodness is called NGES LEGS, which
refers to Nirvana and Buddhahood.
In the first line and a half, Master Nagarjuna said that the
Ten Virtuous Deeds
are the methods to achieve the Dharma.
He refers to higher rebirth and Nirvana, as well as Buddhahood.
CHOS KYI 'BRAS BU 'DI GZHAN DU
Then this line says  The
result of this Buddhist teaching is "this" and "that." Does
anyone want to guess
what "this" and "that" refer to respectively?
You will have a very good outcome in this life and future lives,
dirstha-adirstha, right?
In this life and in future lives, you will see
'DOD PA'I YON TAN RNAM LNGA'O.
In particular, you will receive 'DOD PA'I YON TAN'
good things in the desire realm:
delicious food,
beautiful music, soft blankets.
Think about how wonderful your next life will be when you follow these 10 virtuous deeds.
How comfortable your life will be.
You will have expensive face cream.
I don't know about you, but I'm starting to think
this is strange.
This doesn't seem like something Nagarjuna would say.
You will get a new car.
Your hair will grow back.
You will be full of energy, right?
Then we learned from Master Qiu Ni that
he was actually criticizing, do you understand?
He said, “Oh, that’s great, the ten virtuous deeds.”
- What?
- More money, more cars, more hair.
You'll be very healthy.
Then we learn from Master Chuni that what
Master Nagarjuna wanted to say was:
"Look at how people talk about karma.
Look at how these people talk about karma.
Look at where they want to put karma.
He's criticizing them,
and what he's criticizing goes
deeper than you can imagine.
Getting a lot of money is good.
Getting a nice car is good.
Having a nice apartment is good.
But if you think that the relationship between following the ten virtuous deeds and
getting those things
is inherently real, then that's not right.
- Is it okay to have a nice apartment?
- Yes.
Can I have a lot of money in my bank account? Of
course, that's fine, you can help more people.
Can I have a big car?
Yes. You can take more people
to John Brady's house for a party
[laughs].
But if you think that the relationship between helping others
or reciting the Medicine Buddha mantra
and getting all the good things
is inherently real,
if you think that these connections don't come from you, then something's going to
happen in the next verse. The
next verse reveals what
we're really thinking about. By
the way, I like this,"
Master Chuni said.
He added a comment next to the last sentence.
Here's a photo of
this person holding a plane ticket.
He says, "By the way,
this verse is roughly criticizing those who
focus on using karma to obtain things. It's
not that these things themselves are wrong,
but rather that their feelings about the connection between karma and things are
too deeply ingrained."
They don't understand the emptiness of those connections themselves.
He says, "It's okay,
we can add another line next to this verse and
say: You will get a house, you will have an apartment,
you will become healthy,
and you will also attain enlightenment." [laughs]
He says, "If it were me,
I would add another line to the verse.
So, look at that person holding the plane ticket and passport.
That's the passport to enlightenment.
This also comes from the ten wholesome deeds, okay?"
Then, the next verse reveals Nagarjuna's
view on the previous verse:
,GAL TE BRTAG PA DER 'GYUR NA,
,NYES PA CHEN PO MANG POR 'GYUR,
If you do BRTAG PA
What is BRTAG PA?
B-R-T-A-G
ba rata ta BRTA ga BRTAG
[Ms.] Survey
Yes, survey
If that's the
best investigation you can do about karma,
NYES PA CHEN PO MANG PO,
you'll get into a mountain of
problems. [laughs]
Nagarjuna… it's
a bit like someone else is looking at him and he says, "
Well, I say you should do the ten virtuous deeds
because you can get a lot of wealth."
He says, "My God, think about it, is that how
you do your investigation?
Big trouble, this is huge trouble.
A lot of problems will arise from this.
Reciting the Medicine Buddha mantra
because you think you'll be healthier,
just for that,
and believing there's such a connection between the mantra and health,
NYES PA CHEN PO MANG POR 'GYUR,
then you'll get into a lot of problems afterward,
like?
,DE LTA BAS NA BRTAG PA DE,
,'DIR NI 'THAD PA MA YIN NO,
Nagarjuna goes on to
say, "Your kind of investigation
is a counter-investigation,
okay?
Your investigation is a stupid investigation."
[students laugh]
Okay, understand?
That's an idiotic investigation.
What?
You're using karma just to get some money?
Or perhaps it's just for treating hair problems or something else.
By the way, there's nothing wrong with wanting money, and there's nothing
wrong with wanting more hair. The mistake is
assuming there's an automatic connection between them. The key is
how you perceive the mantra,
not the mantra itself.
Okay,
here are two children.
They are twins.
When you see them,
you might guess it's a picture of twins.
But that's just an assumption. They might
not be twins at all; they might just
look alike.
That is to say, you chant a mantra, and
something might happen afterward,
but is there a connection between the two? Is it
really as you see it?
Okay, let's move on to the
next section.
SANGS RGYAS RNAMS DANG RANG RGYAL DANG,
,NYAN THOS RNAMS KYIS GANG GSUNGS PA'I,
,BRTAG PA GANG ZHIG 'DIR 'THAD PA,
,DE NI RAB TU BRJOD PAR BYA,
By the way,
there's a survey about karma that
you might have done,
and it's a better survey
than a foolish one.
You could have done a wise survey.
Which one?
Well, the Buddha described it.  The
Pratyekabuddha practitioners described it, and the Sravaka
practitioners also spoke of it.
These are all Arhats,
some who have attained Nirvana.
If you want to investigate karma,
I suggest you follow their investigation,
not yours [laughs].
Okay?
Don't think there's an inherent connection between the Medicine Buddha mantra
and money or health.
I suggest you shift your investigation direction
. Shift to where?
Shift to the one the Buddha described,
okay?
Hmm, what is that?
DE NI RAB TU BRJOD PAR BYA.
I'm about to tell you.
I'll explain it to you perfectly.
RAB TU means
I'll make sure you understand 100%.
Then he started a very deep topic,
a very difficult topic.
So finally,
Nagarjuna took off the gloves,
Master Nagarjuna took off his gloves (rolled up his sleeves)
to show you his true style. Let's
begin.
Buckle up.
Let's see...
DPANG RGYA JI LTAR DE BZHIN CHUD,
MI ZA MI ZA LAS NI BU LON BZHIN,
There are many problems with the engraving.
But I understand now.
DPANG RGYA refers to a contract,
usually used for loans.
2000 years ago, when you borrowed money, you
had to sign a DPANG RGYA,
or when you got married, you had to sign a
DPANG RGYA.
So it can be a marriage contract
or a loan agreement.
He said DPANG RGYA DE BZHIN
DPANG RGYA JI LTAR DE BZHIN CHUD. You
have to cross-read.
You have to say CHUD MI ZA.
You know CHUD MI ZA? I've
taught you this again and again in the Stages of the Path. The
Four Laws of Karma:
BYAS PA CHUD MI ZA BA. The
Fourth Law of Karma:
If you do something, you will reap the consequences
(you reap what you sow).
BYAS PA CHUD MI ZA BA.
Literally, BYAS PA means
if you do something,
CHUD MI ZA BA means
it won't disappear over time.
You can't expect to lie to your mother and then to
20 other people lie to you.
Karma won't disappear before 20 people come back to deceive you.
Impossible.
You shouldn't hope you've done something wrong.
Keep quiet, don't tell anyone, and
eventually everyone will forget
because that's not how karma works.
Everything is recorded,
everything spreads.
So, he says this principle,
CHUD MI ZA BA—don't forget this word
because we'll talk about it again and again.
In this part, CHUD MI ZA BA,
in Western Chinese, means that
karma won't disappear automatically just because you wait long enough.
In fact, quite the opposite.
Don't think of CHUD MI ZA BA.
Now, in Abhidharma,
you can take general proof,
but in the Abhidharma school,
this becomes a tool. The
fact of CHUD MI ZA BA, that
is, the fact that karma doesn't disappear out of thin air.
In the Abhidharma system,
it's a separate thing.
It's a real thing,
like a cup or a table.
Hey, did you bring the cup?
Yes. Did you put it on the table?
- Yes.
- How's your CHUD MI ZA BA?
What?  How's
your "fact that karma doesn't disappear"
now?
How are you feeling this morning?
In fact, in Abhidharma,
every time you do anything,
you also do Chud Mi Za Ba.
When you give money,
Got it?
Understand?
You do a good deed for someone, and
you accumulate another Chud Mi Za Ba.
You put another Chud Mi Za Ba
here (in your pocket). This
means that the good deed doesn't just disappear. It
can refer to good or bad behavior. That's how it is
in Abhidharma.
They have a concept like Thob Pa.
When you attain Nirvana,
what connects you to Nirvana?
Actually, in Abhidharma,
this raises a question
because you're no longer there,
but you need to achieve something,
a tangible thing,
like a cup.
Have you achieved something?
- Did you attain Nirvana yesterday? - Yes.
- Did they give you an achievement? - No. Good
heavens, that doesn't hold water.
Go get an achievement! [laughs]
This is called THOB PA.
Now we're going to move on to another topic.
What's it called in English again?
CHUD MI ZA BA, "Never Disappears"?
Did you get a "Never Disappears" guarantee?
When you donated money to the Asian Classics Heritage Library,
did you get a "Never Disappears" guarantee?
Did you ensure that
Paulina gave you a "Never Disappears" guarantee when you donated money to the club?
I'm referring to the Oro club.
Did they also give you a "Never Disappears" guarantee?
Did you get a "Never Disappears" guarantee?
Understand?
In a way, it's like a contract.
We guarantee your future prosperity.
Why?
You just donated money to the
most important project in the universe,
so we give you a written guarantee.
This is what's called DPANG RGYA or
CHUD MI ZA BA'I DPANG RGYA.
That's a "Never Disappears Contract."
Understand?
Because we're going to spend a few hours
explaining this "Never Disappears Contract."
BU LON BZHIN means,
for example, when you take out a loan...
similar to your loan situation,
they give you a contract, and you sign it.
When you take the money, you get that contract,
that "non-disappearing contract."
That "non-disappearing" means that
you can't walk away without repayment.
Okay,
whether you do good or bad,
you'll have a "non-disappearing" contract. Let's
see,
what are we going to delve into?
[Student says] Various "non-disappearing" contracts.
Various "non-disappearing" contracts.
It's a noun, right? Okay.
And this is probably what we'll be discussing next in this chapter.
Now, Nagarjuna will reiterate the
various "non-disappearing" contracts that people have talked about for the past 700 years. What does
"non-disappearing" look like? Let
me tell you
, DE NI KHAMS LAS RNAM PA BZHI,
KHAMS, meaning dhatu, means realm.
Here there are three types: the
"non-disappearing" of the desire realm, the
"non-disappearing" of the form realm,
and the "non-disappearing" of the formless realm.
But he says there are four types. Why?
In the Abhidharma school, there
can be other things outside the realms,
those pure things,
ZAG BCAS, "vimala," undefiled things,
such as Nirvana or Buddhahood.
He says you can obtain them outside of samsara.
One “will not disappear”
So, let’s say there are four kinds for now. Three
belong to the realm of reincarnation,
and one is outside of reincarnation. Who claims these
four “will not disappear”
?
Abhidharma, Abhidharma.
Master Chuni said,
BYE BRAG SMRA BA 'GA' ZHIG. This
means those from the Sarvastivada school, the Abhidharma school.
Okay, first you can divide them into four types
depending on which realm the “will not disappear” belongs to.
What’s the next sentence?
,DE YANG RANG BZHIN LUNG MA BSTAN,
What is LUNG MA BSTAN?
You know
DGE BA, this is not MI DGE BA
- [Student says] Neutral
- Yes, neutral karma.
This sentence is a bit tricky.
Many vessels that hold spiritual things
belong to neutral karma.
So a “will not disappear” contract is neither
good nor bad.
I mean, there
can be bad things in a contract,
and there can be good things in a contract.
But the document, these tools, the
carrier of the contract itself,
is this “will not disappear”.
It is neutral in itself,
like paper.
You can write terrible things on it,
or you can write beautiful things on it.
But this "non-disappearance" itself is neutral. It
can be bad or good.
Okay, next sentence
, SPONG BAS SPANG BA MA YIN TE,
,BSGOM PAS SPANG BA NYID KYANG YIN, There is
an error in the engraving.
I will fix it. Okay
SPONG BAS SPANG BA MA YIN TE is
very important.
It was not eliminated by MTHONG LAM. That's right.
You can see emptiness directly
and it has no effect on "non-disappearance".
Okay, here comes the clever question. By the way,
Nagarjuna is trying to impress us.
What is "non-disappearance"?
What makes karma stick to you?
Well, it's all kinds of "non-disappearance".
What do those "non-disappearances" look like?
From the perspective of karma, it is neutral.
It can also appear in different realms.
Unfortunately, when you see emptiness directly, you
don't just let go of those "non-disappearances".
Maybe you get rid of bad karma.
But those “won’t disappear” are still there.
Okay, that’s a question.
We’re not sure yet.
Okay,
BSGOM PAS SPANG BA NYID KYANG YIN.
But it is indeed eliminated during meditation.
$100 question,
tell me why it should be eliminated during meditation?
$100.
Don’t forget which school we’re in.
If I say a “won’t disappear”
can be eliminated at the end of meditation,
why is that? What happens there?
Lower school, lower school.
[The lady says] The end of suffering.
I want a more precise answer.
$100, at least say two more words.
[Vague answer]
Lower school, lower school.
Okay, reduce to $50.
BEM RIG RGYUN CHAD PA.
Cut off BEM PO and RIG PA,
lower Nirvana.
$12. [Laughter]
Never mind,
BEM PO refers to your physical body,
and RIG PA refers to your consciousness.
RGYUN CHAD PA means…
In the lower schools, you vanish in a flash
[snap fingers]
You vanish in a flash
and then you will no longer suffer, yay! The
debates of the higher schools are
n't so complicated.
What do you think Nirvana is?
[clap]
- You vanish in a flash. - What?
- Your body vanishes in a flash, your consciousness vanishes in a flash, right?
- Right. So
what should we call you then?
- An Arhat. - Where is an Arhat?
[laugh]
[woman] Nowhere
[laugh] That's interesting, it's an ancient debate
[clap]
Where is an Arhat? [laugh]
Okay, maybe
when you… how,
will your "not vanishing" end?
[faint reply]
When your body and consciousness end [laugh]
Okay
, DE PHYIR CHUD MI ZA BA YIS,
,LAS KYI 'BRAS BU SKYED PAR 'GYUR,
Don't forget, we're saying
if the seeds of karma change, we'll have problems, right?
Sorry, if it doesn't change,
it won't produce results.
And if it really does change every moment
[snap fingers]
it disappears every 65 seconds
, then how can it transmit your...
How can there be a CHUD MI ZA BA?
How can there be one, what did we just call it?
[faint answer]
No, the word we just used?
If "not disappearing" is instantaneous,
constantly arising and ceasing,
how can it flow with time?
Then he says here that
DE PHYIR CHUD MI ZA BA YIS
is not the karmic seed that creates the karmic result,
but those "not disappearing"
[students laugh]
seeds come and go,
but those "not disappearing" stay.
When the seed disappears,
those "not disappearing" stay with you.
Then after you donate,
those "not disappearing" give you the money. Do you
understand? The
"not disappearing" stays. Do you
understand? [laughs]
Okay, that's good.
I can see you guys are impressed with this concept. [laughs]
,GAL TE SPONG BAS SPANG BA DANG,
,LAS 'PHO BA YIS  'JIG 'GYUR NA,
if those "non-disappearing" things
would disappear because you reach a higher of the five realms
or something happens to your karma as a whole,
then DE LA LAS 'JIG LA SOGS PA'I,
then LAS BYAS PA CHUD ZA BA (
recite together LAS BYAS PA CHUD ZA BA) [student repeats]
then you could harm others
and never receive any consequences.
This violates every law of karma
and everything the Buddha said.
If "non-disappearing" things could even be
eliminated by higher spiritual attainments,
you could say
you did bad things and didn't have to bear the consequences.
That's impossible, okay?
So "non-disappearing" things must remain [laughs].
Maybe it doesn't create anything,
I don't know
. SKYON RNAMS SU NI THAL BAR 'GYUR,
look at all these problems you've created.
He said SOGS, he also mentioned other problems.
Master Chuni said,
"Are you curious about what the other problems are?"  "
We said, 'Yeah, we really want to know.'
He said, 'LAS MA BYAS
BA DANG MA PHRAD PA
Question three, the third law of karma.
If you don't do it, there won't be a problem.
If you don't steal money,
you'll never lose money. The
third law of karma: If you don't do it,
you won't get the consequences. The
fourth law of karma:
If you do do it, it won't disappear.
Okay, understand?
So, this CHUD MI ZA BA
What law is this? '
Won't disappear.' '
Won't disappear' is so useful
because we still retain the
last two laws of karma.
Okay,
let's continue. By
the way, here's a picture of the Titanic sinking.
Patch, are you ready?
I've been looking for a long time,
you know,
but I couldn't find a picture of the Titanic.
[Students laugh] I
found this one for you. [Laughs]
By the way,
if you have a credit card,
when you boarded the Titanic,
you spent a lot of money on the ship
and then it sank, what
would happen to your DPANG RGYA?
What would happen to your credit card bill?
What would it become?
[Students] Zero. It would
become zero! Okay?"
Your "not disappearing"
sank with the Titanic.
That represents Nirvana.
Your body and consciousness ceased to exist.
That's the sinking of the Titanic, and
your credit card bills sank with it.
Nobody on the Titanic needed to pay for food and drinks.
I'm thinking, maybe not, right?
That company might have gone bankrupt the next day.
Anyway, it's an interesting
example of the cessation of body and consciousness.
Next, all those DPANG RGYA,
all those credit card agreements,
sank with the ship.
Maybe in the end, Nirvana will be defined as
"you escaped your credit card bills."
Why? Because no body or consciousness
remained to pay the bills, understand?
Okay, is
n't this picture cute? Yes,
I think we should take a vacation to
learn the Sanskrit for "not disappearing."
What is the Sanskrit for "not disappearing"?
Come on,
Avipraṇāśa (avipranasha), avipranasha.
Sounds a bit like an Israeli name, right? avi
Avi, pranasha.
It has four parts: a-vi-pra-nasha.
Please repeat a-vi-pra-nasha.
Sorry, it's naasha.
A-vi-pra-naasha
Okay, what does a- mean? Christina
[Christina] No,
no, Vi- means "a lot"
Pra- means "super", and the root √naś
means "lost" or "disappeared"
Understand?
Very, absolutely not disappearing
Absolutely not disappearing
A-vi-pra-naasha, got it?
Now you can say it in Sanskrit
Hey, do you have "not disappearing"?
Sorry, do you have any avipranashas?
Oh, I have some avipranashas I
hope I can keep
those "avipranashas" I donated to the Gold Club
I also hope that when all my credit card debt reaches Nirvana,
those avipranaashas will also disappear Okay
Learn this word
Usually in Sanskrit, √naś is the root
meaning can be destroyed or lost
It is likely to be associated with "not" Next
section By
the way, this is indeed a very long chapter, I'm sorry
But I know you are all fascinated
Now another person says
So, if your "not disappearing"
really disappears
Sounds a bit like kosher pastry.
[Student laughs]
Really? I don't know
where that nice bakery is. Is it
still there?
In...?
[Woman] On Second Avenue?
Yes, no?
[Woman] Sometimes open, sometimes closed.
Always like that. Really?
That shop's been there for almost a hundred years. [
Woman] Yes, hopefully it'll reopen.
Okay, anyway,
you can go there and get some avipranashas to go back with. The
man said, "Okay.
" "I understand. If the Titanic sank,
all the credit card bills would be gone.
But what about from this life to the next?"
"When you reach another life,
will you lose your avipranaashas?
When you cross the border,
NYING MTSAMS SBYOR BA
"and be born into a new life,
will these avipranahas follow you?" Will
these "not disappear" still
follow you?
First, you guys guess what the
[students] will think.
Will they disappear?
[Student] No,
they probably won't disappear.
Otherwise, there wouldn't be any karma in the next life.
Okay, here's the real answer
: KHAMS MTSUNGS LAS NI CHA MTSUNGS DANG,
If you reincarnate in the same realm,
if you are reborn as a human again,
you will carry your avipranashas.
Or if you are reborn from the desire realm to the desire realm,
CHA MI MTSUNGS PA THAMS CAD KYI,
but when you go to other realms in reincarnation,
some may not carry avipranashas
because those celestial beings
don't experience the obvious suffering you feel in the human realm,
right?
If you are reborn from the human realm to the human realm,
you will experience some great suffering that celestial beings don't have.
So if you go from the human realm to the celestial realm,
some of your troublesome avipranashas
may have encountered some problems
because they (celestial beings) don't have afflictions there.  Do you understand?
Okay, what
I mean is, when you are reborn from a human to a celestial being,
in that life you
won't experience the intense suffering you felt in the human realm.
No one loses an arm in the celestial realm;
it won't happen.
So, it's very possible that when you go from the human realm
to another realm,
something happens to your avipranashas.
But, are you ready?  I
'm sorry,
your karma may not follow you,
but your avipranasha will.
What does that mean?
Your karma may not follow you,
but your karma, what we call it...
your "non-disappearance" will follow you, how about that?
These are all Abhidharma.  Okay, sorry.
By the way, the only reason
Nagarjuna gave so many
crazy ideas about Abhidharma
is that he will completely overturn them at some crucial point.
[Everyone laughs]
I'm just telling you the
next sentence.
Sorry, the next sentence
, MTHONG BA'I CHOS LA RNAM GNYIS PO,
MTHONG BA'I CHOS refers to what
you see on the path of seeing,
but it can also mean dirsta-adirsta.
Seeing in this life or seeing in a future life. That's what it
means.
Will you see it? That
is, dirsta-adirsta.
When you do any kind of... how should we say it? At
any time in this life,
your "non-disappearance" in this life is dirsta.
You will get it in this life,
no matter what karma you create in this life.
You will get something "non-disappearance" for it in this life.
Dirsta refers to what you see in this life.
RNAM GNYIS PO.
In the Abhidharma system, this
also applies to ZAG BCAS or ZAG MED.
Good karma... impure karma or pure karma.
This is a very long topic
. KUN GYI  [THAMS CAD] LAS DANG LAS KYI DE,
Furthermore, chetana and chetayitva,
these two kinds of
chetana and chetayitva,
we learned them a long time ago, just yesterday
[students laughing]
Chetana comes from √cit
[faint reply]
Chetana,
yes, that's right.
Motivation and intention.
He said,
whether you create karma consciously
or because of what you are thinking,
you will still get a "non-disappearing" karma.
Whether it's mental karma, that is, "thought" karma, that
is, motivation, or actions or words driven by motivation,
you will still get a "non-disappearing" karma.
That's all the details of "non-disappearing" karma.
Avipranasha
, THA DAD PAR NI SKYE 'GYUR ZHING,
This is cool.
Every time you create karma,
you get a separate "non-disappearing" karma.
So basically you accumulate "non-disappearing" karma your whole life. You
carry "non-disappearing" karma in your pocket your whole life.
Every little thing you do,
you get a new "non-disappearing" karma.
It's silent.  The text
here says THA DAD, THA DAD PAR SKYE.
It quietly arises
, RNAM PAR SMIN KYANG GNAS PA YIN.
This is really controversial.
After the karma matures, it "won't disappear" and follows you.
So what will it do? [laughs]
Don't ask me,
he didn't say, but according to Abhidharma,
"not disappearing" will still follow you
even if the karmic cause is destroyed, ripened,
or ended.
Even if the seed ends,
"not disappearing" will still follow you in some way.
So we must be accumulating
millions of "not disappearing" things.
If they no longer carry karma,
what will they do?  I don't know either.
00:35:44,300 --> 00:35:46,290z It's
a bit like the
empty pocket you have after you've spent all your money.
I guess that pocket will still be there, right?
Now, the Abhidharma people say, "Master Nagarjuna,
you forgot to tell them
how to get rid of your 'non-disappearing' karma."
Master Nagarjuna says, "Ah, yes, let's talk about it."
Here we begin to talk about
how to get rid of the "non-disappearing" karma. The
extra "non-disappearing" karma.
Okay
, DE NI 'BRAS BU 'PHO BA DANG,
,SHI BAR GYUR NA 'GAG PAR 'GYUR,
Here the second part is simple.
If you SHI BA,
you lose all the "non-disappearing" karma.
[Student] If you die,
yes, if you die,
you lose part of the "non-disappearing" karma. It does
n't seem to make sense
because you should carry it into the next life.
'BRAS BU 'PHO BA' means serious,
heavy, mature karma.
This refers to a kind of Stream-entry.  The
Sakadagami, Anagami, and Arhat fruits
are collectively known as the four fruits of a Shramana.
If it is a very large fruit, an extremely good deed, a
significant spiritual realization,
"then, your 'non-disappearance' can be eliminated."
I don't know.
I'm imagining the
level of mastery of SBYOR LAM BZOD SBYOR LAM.
You will never go to a lower realm again,
so they must have destroyed
your "non-disappearance."
It must have destroyed part of your "non-disappearance."
But then he said that it can only disappear
when you become an Arhat.
I don't know.
Okay
, DE YI RNAM DBYE ZAG MED DANG,
,ZAG DANG BCAS PAR SHES PAR BYA,
You can have the "non-disappearance" of attaining enlightenment,
or you can have the "non-disappearance" of continuous samsara.
Everyone in the room is going to fall asleep. Let's
see if we can continue. [laughs]
Patch, I like this picture.
I built a house for my guru. It cost
me... wait, there's another picture of him. Yes,
I built a house for my guru.
I paid for it, I built it myself,
and no one helped me.
Maybe one day someone would come and lend a hand.
I was standing so high up...
It was two stories high, and I was on the third floor,
on a ladder. I'll never forget it.
It was winter, the dead of winter.
I was on the ladder, painting the house like this. Then
some people would come over,
some old Mongolian men, and
they would say, "Hey, Mike."
I said, "What's wrong?"
He said, "I have to go to the store."
I said, "I'm painting the house, and
nobody's helping me."
Then he said, "But I need to go to the store, and I
need you to give me a ride."
I am SPYI PA'I RTA.
I am the community's public carriage.
Why am I telling this story?
If you get to a high enough place and
you leave your toolbox down below,
if you work on the third floor,
you'll often forget some tools.
You'll have to climb up and down this dangerous ladder, go
down two floors, grab a screwdriver, and then go back up.
Then you forget the paint,
and you're all alone. What
I'm trying to say is that
if you get to a high enough place,
you can put some of your "non-disappearing" ideas behind you.
I don't know why this picture is used.
Okay,
let's move on to the next verse.
Now we start talking, start thinking about
this whole "non-disappearing" thing. It
starts to sound a little uncomfortable.
It really feels like some very low-school ideas.
Once you create karma, it doesn't disappear. It
starts to feel a little uncomfortable, right?
This whole concept of "not disappearing"
sounds strange.
Then, Nagarjuna suddenly shifted gears and
said the following verse: ,
STONG PA NYID DANG TSAD MED DANG,
,'KHOR BA DANG NI RTAG PA MIN,
,LAS RNAMS CHUD MI ZA BA'I CHOS,
,SANGS RGYAS KYIS NI BSTAN PA YIN,
Who taught "not disappearing"?
- [Student] Buddha
- Buddha
Nagarjuna said, "Hey,
don't think 'not disappearing'
is a stupid concept.
There's a real 'not disappearing'."
He shifted gears here and
said, "Look,
I know you people
don't really value these 'not disappearing' concepts now, but there really is a 'not disappearing' concept.
Let me tell you about this
real 'not disappearing' concept."
Then he began to describe
STONG PA NYID:
Don't think that because things are empty,
it can destroy this "not disappearing."
"Not disappearing" does exist,
and it is empty,
but that doesn't mean
it won't preserve your seeds,
okay?
Don't think that those things that "won't disappear"
can't bear your karma and follow you through countless lifetimes. It's
precisely because they are empty that you
misunderstand emptiness.
When I say "won't disappear" is emptiness,
I don't mean it doesn't work,
because you always think that way.
Every time I say emptiness,
you think it
means it's irrelevant.
But when I say emptiness, I mean
this is what matters [laughs].
"Won't disappear" is emptiness,
so you'd better understand them
and respect them,
because it means they work,
not that they don't.
This is the
first thing Nagarjuna said.
STONG PA NYID CHAD PA
CHAD PA means…
When we say BEM RIG RGYUN CHAD PA,
when you cut off the flow of something,
we say "cut off."
[Vague response]
Cease? Cut off
[Vague response] It
should be CHAD PA, STONG
PA NYID DANG CHAD PA DANG.
Oh, that's…
Ah, that must be wrong.
I mixed the Tanjur version and the Chuni version
together
so I could spot the problem.
I have the Chuni version;
you have the Tanjur version.  The
reason I did that is
that it helps to discover some problems.
STONG PA NYID DANG CHAD PA DANG
Don't think that because it is empty,
your "not disappearing" will disappear.
CHAD PA—cut off.
We have two extreme views:
believing that things are unchanging
and believing that things just stop.
Third point,
'KHOR BA,
you'd better understand
this so-called "not disappearing."
Nagarjuna said, "Firstly,
because it was said by the Buddha; secondly,
because it is the king of samsara,
it governs samsara.
'Not disappearing' governs samsara.
They are the bus drivers of samsara. The
'not disappearing' in your karmic pocket
is the bus driver of your samsara.
So you'd better understand it!"
Because it is these things that
cause your karma to follow you,
you'd better understand it.
He said this isn't nonsense; it is indeed true.
This is what the Buddha said, and
we must understand it
because they govern your suffering.
Finally,
RTAG PA MIN,
don't think they are unchanging. That's wrong. Don't think that these
accumulated karmic forces will remain unchanged over time.
That's also a misunderstanding.
The Buddha did say that
karma accumulates over time
and returns to you,
but this doesn't mean karma is unchanging; it
means karma is constantly compounding.
He's saying that
I've made many jokes about the Abhidharmas in the verses of these chapters,
but they're actually quite cool. This
idea that karma doesn't disappear
is true, absolutely true.
He said,
"I just brought it up because you think that
if 'it doesn't disappear' is emptiness,
it doesn't work.
But I want to tell you that if it is emptiness,
that's precisely the powerful evidence that it works and karma follows
you."
"So you'd better take good care of your karma.
" This "it doesn't disappear" thing is true.
Why? - That's what the Buddha said.
That's what Nagarjuna said.
It felt like a very long class,
but that's okay, right?
00:44:33,368 --> 00:44:35,361
Okay, let's continue. ,
GANG PHYIR LAS NI SKYE BA MED, ,
'DI LTAR RANG BZHIN MED DE'I PHYIR,
,GANG PHYIR DE NI MA SKYES PA,
,DE PHYIR CHUD ZAR MI 'GYUR RO,
Nagarjuna began to talk about why
"not disappearing" should be effective.
Nagarjuna entered into why
He said, LAS NI SKYE BA MED,
"not disappearing" is effective because
you cannot create karma.
"Not disappearing" is effective because
you cannot create karma. What does this
mean, which has inherent existence?
Now he said, oh, finally you're all confused.
[Everyone laughs]
I'll say it again,
"not disappearing" is effective
because you cannot create karma.
"Not disappearing" is effective
'DI LTAR
Why?
Because karma itself has no inherent existence.
It comes from your seeds.
And because you cannot create karma,
it will always follow you and will not leave. Because you cannot create karma,
it will always follow you
and will not simply disappear. Because you cannot create karma,
therefore you do indeed obtain "not disappearing."
Understand?
Because you cannot create karma,
you do obtain those "not disappearing."
[Christina] It sounds like karma
and "not disappearing" are the same thing.
Well, "not disappearing" allows karma
to remain on Christina,
regardless of who Christina refers to here. [
Christina] Like glue?
Yes, like glue.
This is a very Abhidharma thought. Let me say this,
if you really want to ask,
what makes the glue stick to you? That's
right, the
Abhidharma says, THOB PA'I THOB PA.
You need to have a bottle of glue to have glue.
And then some other people say, do
you have THOB PA'I THOB PA'I THOB PA?  Does
your glue contain glue to stick things?
They say no, and then it
ends at the part about "glue containing glue"
[laughter].
Okay, do
n't worry.
You don't need glue to glue things.
You don't need glue containing glue to glue things,
but you do need glue to glue things.
Okay,
I like this picture below, called "Laws."
Why things work.
Laws.
I like to say: because laws don't exist, they are real.
You must follow the laws of karma.
00:47:17,110 --> 00:47:18,890 Because
they don't exist. That
means even the laws of karma come from you.
Geshe, then they should be adjustable at any time.
If the laws of karma come from me,
then I should be able to do a good deed
and get a bad result.
In some special cases,
if it comes from me,
then I should be able to mess up the laws of karma.
That's a fallacy. The
fact that some things come from you
doesn't mean you can change them. It
doesn't mean there are no fixed patterns. It doesn't mean there are
no necessary rules. The
fact that some things come from you does
n't prove that there are no necessary laws in life.
That is to say, if you hurt someone...
You will inevitably be harmed
– isn't it the law you created? – Yes
– Can you change that law? – No.
But if it came from me, I could change it.
MA KHYAB – Maybe not,
okay?
[Clapping]
We'll talk about this later.
This is a difficult lesson.
Listen to it a few more times.
We haven't finished investigating karma yet.
We have one more lesson to go.
See you next time.